Finding Aid of the Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000 Records, 1975-1989
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000 Records, 1975-1989
Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000
UWM Manuscript Collection 143
2.2 cubic ft. (3 boxes)
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
This collection contains the administrative records of Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000, a volunteer, community-based organization interested in improving the quality of life for citizens of Greater Milwaukee. The majority of the records in this collection date from 1980 to 1983. Through correspondence, minutes and agendas, publications, papers, and photographs this collection documents the efforts of a citizen group to develop a positive and realistic vision for Milwaukee in the year 2000, and to make suggestions for achieving that vision. Of particular interest are the ten final reports of the Goals 2000 task forces and the final report of its successor, Action for Goals 2000.
Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000 began in 1978 when Wilfred Kraegel convened a small group of people to discuss the possibility of a Milwaukee Goals Project. In May of 1979, the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Division of Urban Outreach funded a Milwaukee Goals Forum at which approximately sixty Milwaukee area leaders met with experienced Goals leaders from other cities. In November of 1979, the Milwaukee Journal sponsored a daylong program featuring speakers from business, academia, government and labor to look at Milwaukee's future. Between January and June 1980, the Milwaukee 2000 Planning Group, co-chaired by Wilfred Kraegel and Anthony Catanese, met monthly to establish a broad outline of the project including their purpose, the geographic area they would cover, a time frame, and the committee structure. In July, the planning group approved the papers of incorporation, established themselves as an interim board, appointed a nominating committee to develop the permanent board and empowered an interim steering committee, chaired by Jean Tyler, to continue planning a Goals project for the Greater Milwaukee area. In October 1980, over 100 community leaders were selected to serve on the board of directors.
On December 3, 1980, Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000 was officially launched at a public meeting. Invitations were sent to over 1,000 area leaders and organizations. Included with the invitation was a brief description of the Goals project and a survey form asking if they wished to participate. In addition, area leaders were asked to respond to the list of suggested topics for study. The Milwaukee Journal also created an insert for their newspaper and for general distribution so that citizens could respond with suggested topics. On the basis of the results from these surveys, the interim steering committee approved nine areas for study by the Goals project: 1) arts, recreation and culture, 2) communication, 3) economy/employment, 4) education, 5) health and social welfare, 6) housing, 7) land use, 8) public safety, and 9) transportation. Frank Horton and Harry Franke were chosen as project co-chairs for Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000. Jean B. Tyler became the executive director in August of 1981. Task force co-chairs were appointed by the interim steering committee. Between 1981 and 1983, the task forces and their various committees and subcommittees, conducted research and worked with community citizens and organizations to create recommendations for improving the Greater Milwaukee area. The final reports of each of the task forces were made public in the spring 1983.
In 1983, a follow-up group, Action for Goals 2000, was established to encourage continuing attention to the agenda of Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000, and to monitor community progress. Action for Goals 2000's final report focused on the growing gap between Milwaukee's "haves" and "have nots," and paid particular attention to racism.
The files are organized alphabetically, then chronologically. Files contain a variety of materials, including correspondence, minutes and agendas, task force and special committee reports, newspaper clippings, and photographs.
Related Material in the UWM Libraries
Library Council of Southeastern Wisconsin Records UWM Manuscript Collection 48
Records of the Henry W. Maier Administration Milwaukee Series 44
UW-Extension Center for Community Economic Development Records UWM Archival Collection 154
UW-Milwaukee Office of the Chancellor Records UWM Archival Collection 46
UW-Milwaukee Office of the Provost and Vice Chancellor for Academic Affairs Records UWM Archival Collection 12
UW-Milwaukee Photographs Collection UWM Archival Collection 6
Wilfred A. Kragel Papers UWM Manuscript Collection 137
Administrative/Restriction Information
There are no access restrictions on the materials, and the collection is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
Jean Tyler donated the collection to the Wisconsin Historical Society in 1986. The unprocessed collection was transferred to the UWM Libraries' Archives in March of 1999. Jean Tyler donated a second accession (98-057) to the Archives in April 1999. A scrapbook of material was donated in March of 2017 by Barbara J Michaels at the behest of Jean Tyler.
Contents List
- Action for Goals 2000, Miscellaneous, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Action for Goals 2000 1983-1989, Publication, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Action for Goals 2000-An Introduction, Publication, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Ad Hoc Committee on Education, Agendas, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Ad Hoc Committee on Education, Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Ad Hoc Committee on Education, Miscellaneous, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Ad Hoc Committee on Inter-Local Relationships, Report, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Ad Hoc Committee on Minority Relations and Goal Attainment, Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ad Hoc Committee on Minority Relations and Goal Attainment, Minutes and Agendas, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Ad Hoc Committee on Planning, Implementation and Leadership, Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Ad Hoc Committee on Planning, Implementation and Leadership, Minutes, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Advisory Committee, Miscellaneous, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Advisory Committee, Public Officials, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- An Analytical Account of Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000, Paper, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Arts, Recreation and Culture Task Force, Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Arts, Recreation and Culture Task Force, Final Report, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Arts, Recreation and Culture Task Force, Minutes and Agendas, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Arts, Recreation and Culture Task Force, Preliminary Report, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Arts, Recreation and Culture Task Force, "Purpose Statement/Universal Goals," undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Charitable Organization Annual Report and Registration Statement, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Clippings, 1979-1983 and undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Committee and Task Force Membership Rosters, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Committee Chairs, Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Communications Task Force, Agendas, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Communications Task Force, Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Communications Task Force, Issues, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Communications Task Force, Preliminary Report, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Communications/Marketing Committee, Correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Communications/Marketing Committee, Minutes and Agendas, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Conclusion of Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000, Program, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Deciding Our Future, Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000, 1981-1983, Publication, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Economy/Employment Task Force, Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Economy/Employment Task Force, Final Report, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Economy/Employment Task Force, Miscellaneous, 1982 and undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Economy/Employment Task Force, Preliminary Report, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Economy/Employment Task Force and Subcommittee, Minutes and Agendas, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Education Task Force, Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Education Task Force, Final Report, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Education Task Force, Miscellaneous, 1982 and undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Education Task Force, Preliminary Report, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Executive Committee, Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Executive Committee, Minutes, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Financial Information, 1980-1981, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Goal Post, The, Newsletter, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- "Goals 2000 Recommendations," 1983 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Goals 2000 Survey, External Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Goals 2000 Survey, Miscellaneous, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Goals 2000 Survey, Print Survey, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Goals 2000 Survey, Survey Results, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- "Goals 2000 Timeline," undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
- "Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000, A Process Report," 1983 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- "Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000, An Historical Overview," undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
- "Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000, Projecting Probable and Preferable Scenarios," undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
- "Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000, Public Response Phase, An Initial Report," 1982 (Box 1, Folder 60)
- "Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000, The Chronology of a Community Dream," Paper, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- "Goals for Milwaukee 2000," undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- "Goals for Milwaukee 2000, An Overview," 1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- "Goals Language," undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Grant Proposals, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Health and Social Well-Being Task Force, Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Health and Social Well-Being Task Force, Final Report, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Health and Social Well-Being Task Force, Minutes and Agendas, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Health and Social Well-Being Task Force, Miscellaneous, 1981-1982 and undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Health and Social Well-Being Task Force, Preliminary Report, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Housing Task Force, Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Housing Task Force, Final Report, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Housing Task Force, Minutes and Agendas, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Housing Task Force, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Housing Task Force, Preliminary Report, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "Implementation Phase of Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000," Paper, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Information Committee, Correspondence, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Information Committee, Minutes and Agendas, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Interim Steering Committee, Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Interim Steering Committee, Minutes and Agendas, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Land Use Task Force, Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Land Use Task Force, Final Report, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Land Use Task Force, Miscellaneous, 1982 and undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Land Use Task Force, Preliminary Report, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Land Use Task Force and Subcommittee, Minutes and Agendas, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Metropolitan Milwaukee Goals Forum, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 66)
- Milwaukee Goals/Action 2000: Assess 88, Final Report, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Milwaukee Journal Forum: Goals for Greater Milwaukee 2000, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Miscellaneous, 1979-1983 and undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Nominating Committee, Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- "Organizational Glossary," undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Organizational Structure, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Outreach/Education Committee, Correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Outreach/Education Committee, Minutes and Agendas, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Pamphlets, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Photographs, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Planning Group, Minutes and Agendas, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Pointing the Way... Greater Milwaukee/2000: Neighborhood Perspectives, Paper, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Potentials, Paper, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Pre-Goals Planning Project, Miscellaneous, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Presentation Announcements, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Press Releases, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Project Co-Chairs, Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- "Project Scope-Project Overview-Introduction," undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
- "Proposed Citizen Response Techniques and Timetable," Draft, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Public Safety Task Force, Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Public Safety Task Force, Final Report, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Public Safety Task Force, Miscellaneous, 1982 and undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Public Safety Task Force, Preliminary Report (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Public Safety Task Force and Subcommittees, Agendas, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Report Coordinating Committee, Correspondence, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 67)
- "Resolution Opposing Certain Goals of Goals Greater Milwaukee/2000 Relative to Regional Government," 1982 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Scrapbook, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
- "Some Commonly Asked Questions and Answers," undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Special Committee Reports, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- "Suggested Speech Outline," undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Task Force, Brochures, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- "Task Force Guidelines, Mission Statements" Draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
- "Task Force Guidelines, Scheduling," undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Task Forces, Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Task Forces, Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Taxation Subcommittee, Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Taxation Subcommittee, Minutes and Agendas, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 58)
- "Tentative Categories of Goals," 1980 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Transportation Task Force, Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Transportation Task Force, Final Report, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Transportation Task Force, Miscellaneous, 1981 and undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
- Transportation Task Force, Preliminary Report, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 63)
- Transportation Task Force and Subcommittees, Agendas, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 64)
- Youth Involvement, Correspondence and Agendas, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 65)